陈部长 看这意思
Director Chen, it appears
你们要和中共相逢一笑泯恩仇喽
you will kiss and make up with the CPC.
李参政员不高兴
You don't approve?
哼 若论对中共的了解
You don't know the CPC
你们不如我们
like we do.
当年你们和中共眉来眼去的时候
While you were making passes at them,
我们在法国
we fought them head on
已经跟他们打得头破血流了
in France.
听说你要辞职
I heard you intend to resign.
就是辞职
Even if you resign,
也得参加完南京的受降仪式
wait till after the capitulation ceremony in Nanjing
你是抗日的功臣
You helped defeat the Japanese.
仪式上不得没有你这个民族英雄
The ceremony needs a national hero like you.
我若不递辞呈啊
If I don't resign,
很快就成了内战的罪人了
I'll be blamed for the civil war.
欢迎毛先生
Welcome, Mr. Mao
欢迎毛先生来重庆
Welcome to Chongqing, Mr. Mao.
八年抗战
We've been fighting the enemy
与国家的敌人作战
for 8 years.
打光了拼光了
It's my job
没话说
to fight till the end.
可如今胜利了
Now that we won,
还打
why
打谁呀
are we stilling fighting?
中国人打中国人
I will not
这种事我不干
fight my own kind.
马林诺夫斯基元帅
General Malinovsky has agreed
同意向我们移交东北三省了
to hand over the Northeast provinces.
这么说 可以不用打了
No need to fight anymore?
不打 已经到手的地盘
If we don't,
中共肯让出来吗
will the CPC hand over their turf?
各位 各位
Ladies and gentlemen.
委员长 毛先生提议
Chairman Chiang and Mr. Mao propose a toast
为了和平 干杯
To peace, cheers.
干杯
Cheers.
蒋主席
Chairman Chiang.
蒋主席好
Hello, Chairman Chiang
毛先生好
Hello, Mr. Mao.
我是《中央日报》的记者
I'm from the "Central Daily".
我注意到今天两位都穿着中山装
I notice you're both wearing Mandarin suit.
那在今天这样一个特别的日子里
On a special day like today,
一样的着装有什么特殊的含义吗
is there a special meaning for that?
中山装
The Mandarin suit
是民国政府公务人员的正式着装
is the official attire for all civil servants of the Nationalist Government.
中正
As the Chairman
身为国府主席
of KMT,
今天是代表政府
it's my duty
迎候毛先生茬临陪都
to welcome Mr. Mao to Chongqing.
自然要穿中山装以显庄重
I'm wearing the Mandarin suit out of respect.
请问毛先生 您也是同样的原因吗
Mr Mao, is that your reason too?
原因很简单
The reason is simple
委员长和我都是中山先生的弟子
Chairman Chiang and I are both Dr. Sun's disciples.
国共两党继承的
Both the KMT and the CPC have inherited
是中山先生民主革命的衣钵
Dr. Sun's revolutionary legacy.
同宗同源 存续相依
We share the same roots.
中山先生的传人都穿中山装
It is only natural that
那是再自然不过了
Dr. Sun's disciples should wear the Mandarin suits
毛先生 对不起
Mr. Mao. Excuse me.
Pardon me, Mr Mao.
鄙人今天看到你们二位站在一起
To see you standing next to each other,
确实有一些激动和兴奋
I can't help but feel excited
我就是还想再问毛先生一个问题
I have another question for Mr. Mao
就是在即将开始的谈判中 您认为关于
In the upcoming negotiation
政治民主化的问题
ith regards to the issue of democracy,
国共两党能够找到共同点吗
will the Parties find common ground
或者达成共识
or reach any consensus?
只要找 共同点总会有的
Definitely, if you look hard enough.
刚才这位记者先生
This reporter already noticed
不是已经为我们找到了一个共同点吗
we had something in common.
目前 共军华北一部
The North China division of the CPC
山东大部
and the Shandong division
正在向东北渗透
are infiltrating the Northeast
新四军陈毅所部
Chen Yi's New Fourth Army
也在沪杭周边地域活动
is active around Shanghai and Hangzhou,
给国府还都南京造成了很大的困难
making it difficult for the Nationalist Government to move the capital back to Nanjing.
我军大部目前距离这些地区都太远了
Our troops are too far away from these regions.
美军已经在青岛登陆
The Americans have landed in Qingdao.
并且承诺派飞机和军舰
They promised to send planes and warships
将国军运往东北 华北
to get our troops to the Northeast, North China,
华东及江南各地
East China and south of Yangtze River
东北就拜托杜将军了
General Du, I'm counting on you in the Northeast
表老有什么意见 就请直说
Master Zhang, please give us your honest opinion.
我们共产党
The CPC
一向是有话摆在桌面上讲的
likes to keep things in the open.
我们从来不隐瞒自己的观点
We never hide our views
也会尊重民盟和其他朋友的意见
and respect those of our friends and the China Democratic League.
张表老
Sir?
哎哟 谢谢
Thank you.
既然是朋友 老夫也就实话实说
I'll be honest with you, as a friend.
民主联合政府
To form a democratic coalition government,
是国家和平 统一 团结的唯一途径
peace and unity are the only ways forward.
蒋先生和毛先生能够坐在一起谈
If Mr. Chiang and Mr. Mao can sit down and talk,
这确实是难能可贵哟
it would be wonderful
既然是谈判 就需要让步和妥协
A negotiation requires concessions and compromises
只有这样才可能换来和平
in order to bring about peace
毛主席能够亲自来重庆
Chairman Mao came to Chongqing
这本身就代表了我党的诚意啊
That alone proves our sincerity.
这地盘和军队都是细枝末节
The turf and army are minor details.
与其在拥有多少地盘和军队上斤斤计较
Rather than haggle over them,
我们何不各党派联合起来呢
why not unify all the parties?
就在此刻
At this moment,
国民党的军队正频繁调动 四面出击
the Nationalist Army is busy
对我党在各地建立的民主政权
in regions where we have set up our regime
实施战略包围和试探性进攻
with strategic blockades or explorative attacks.
蒋先生视八路军新四军
The Eighth Route Army and New Fourth Army
为眼中钉肉中刺啊
are thorns in Mr. Chiang's flesh.
说句诛心之论
Pardon me for saying this
若不是有我们这几十万条破枪
If we didn't have a few hundred thousand used guns,
蒋先生会跟我们这些人坐下来谈吗
Mr. Chiang would never sit down and talk to us.
润公
Ze
国共两党如果都不在军权上松手
If neither Party let go,
兵争不止
the war will go on.
那么和平民主 从何谈起呀
You can forget about peace.
双方谈判 都不让步
If neither Party gives in,
肯定谈不拢啊
negotiation will break down.
表老居中调停
I appreciate
这个情我领啊
your mediation.
也罢
Very well.
为了早日实现和平民主建国
For the sake of peace and democracy,
我们就先让一步
we'll make the first concession
在未来国防军一百个师的编制里
Among the 100 divisions of the national defense army,
我党原先要求的四十八个师
our request for 48 divisions
已经减为二十个师
has been cut back to 20 divisions
我们在江南的八个解放区
We're willing to give up 8 liberated regions
也可以让出来
in south of Yangtze River.
希望我党的妥协和让步
I hope that our concession
能够有助于政治协商会议的召开
will set the consultative meeting in motion
和联合政府的成立
and help set up a coalition government.
下面我代表美国政府和杜鲁门总统
I'm here on behalf of President Truman and the United States government
发表如下声明
to issue the following statement.
我们无意支持
We have no intention to support
麦淇淋式的共产主义者夺取中国
a '‘Cream of Wheat" Marxist to take over China.
中国现政府及蒋介石先生
The present Nationalist Government of China and Mr. Chiang Kai-shek
是美国人民忠诚的朋友
are faithful friends of the United States.
我们唯一关心的是
Our only concern is
雅尔塔会议和苏中友好同盟条约
whether the Yalta Conference and
是否能够得到重庆政府
the Sino-Russian Friendship Alliance Treaty
的尊重和遵守
will be honored and implemented by the Chongqing government.
美国深知
The United States is cognizant that
现时中国国民政府为一党政府
the Nationalist government of China is a one-party government
并相信假如国民政府之基础如能更加扩大
and believes that peace, unity and democratic reform in China
容纳国内其他主要政治分子
can be furthered if the basis of this government
则中国和平 统一 民主的革新
is broadened to include
必能更进一步
other political elements in the country.
下面我代表中国共产党发表如下声明
On behalf of the CPC, I wish to issue the following statement.
我党欢迎杜鲁门总统十五日
We welcome President Truman's China policy as per the declaration on the 15th
对华政策声明中关于国民党 共产党
with regards to the cease fire
及其他不同意见的武装部队之间
between the KMT, CPC
停止敌对行动
and other political parties
召开各党派代表会议
and to call upon a multi-party meeting
结束国民党一党专政
to implement reforms
改组国民政府
to end the KMT's one-party dictatorship
为各党派获有公平
and to ensure fair and
有效的代表权的泛代议制政府
effective representation of all parties
借以实现中国之民主统一的建议
to facilitate the democratic unification of China.
杜鲁门总统的特使
President Truman's special envoy,
马歇尔就快到了
Marshall, is arriving soon
他是来调停国共内战的
to mediate in the civil war.
不能轻慢
Don't slight him.
是和是打
Peace or war,
你心里有数才行
you should know better.
想和的时候可以和
Stop when we want to stop
想打的时候可以打
Fight when we want to fight.
只有这样
This is the only case.
我们说了才算数
Not until we say so.
本次协商会议
The purpose of this Assembly
致力于政治民主化
is to seek political reforms towards democracy.
在协商基础上
The basis of our negotiation
力求组建多党派联合政府
is to establish a multi-party coalition government
以期和平统一之早日实观
to facilitate a peaceful unification.
介公
Kai,
国府席位三十几个
there are over 30 seats in the Senate.
一下子就让出去八个
We have to give up 8 of them?
让出八个
To give up 8 seats
就得赶走八个
is to oust 8 of our men
把乌纱帽送给外人
and hand them to someone else
这天下 还是国民党的吗
Who owns the world now? It's hardly KMT.
父亲
Father
CC他们在私下串联
Central Club and the others have secretly agreed
拒绝承认政治协商会议
not to acknowledge the CPPCC
并且反对让位给民盟和中共
and refused to give up their seats for the CDL and CPC.
要是这么闹下去
There'II be trouble
会出大事的
if they keep this up.
各位同学 各位师长
Fellow students, teachers
各位川中父老
and friends of Sichuan.
五个月前 我们在这里相聚
5 months ago, we gathered here
庆祝民族抗战之伟大胜利
to celebrate a national victory.
欺人太甚 放下你的鞭子
That's outrageous. Lower your whip.
你少管闲事
Mind your own business.
这是我家的姑娘
She's my girl.
容不得别人来管
You have no say
谁给她饭吃
Whoever feeds her,
谁就有权利使用他
owns her
住手 为什么打人
Hey Stop it.
姑娘
Are you alright, Miss?
谁在开枪 谁
Who fired that shot? Who was it?
谁 谁开枪
Who was it? Who fired that shot?
冯长官
Sir.
市区里边 不让开枪
No open fire in the city, Sir.
例许他们行凶打人
But they can beat people up?
我不管你是哪家的王八蛋
I don't care who you work for.
回去给我冯玉祥带句话
Send a message for me.
有本事明着来
Don't sneak around.
别那么下作
Stop this underhanded nonsense
号外 号外 蒋委员长开大会了
Extra: Mr. Chiang calls for a meeting.
买报
Newspaper.
来啦
Here
这回老蒋撕破脸了
Chiang has taken the gloves off.
要撇开我们召开一党国大
He's calling the National People's Congress without us.
蒋介石在玩独角戏
It's his one-man show.
国大召开的日期能早一天确定
The sooner we set the date for the NPC,
美国的援助也就能早一天落实
the sooner the US will confirm their assistance.
开国大只有一个国民党是不成的
We can't have the NPC with the KMT alone.
既然中共不来 那就算了
We can forget the CPC.
摆花瓶 有那些民主党派也就可以了
For appearance, we still have the other parties
中共和中间党派
The CPC and the other parties
坚持重庆的政协会议决议
insisted on implementing the resolution of the CPPCC in Chongqing.
这事 可怎么解决呀
What will you do?
对于张澜呢 安抚为主
Pacify Zhang Lan.
对于中共 就要一面打一面哄喽
Coax and fight the CPC at the same time.
什么时候毛泽东的军队打光了
When Mao runs out of troops,
也就不用再哄了
we can stop coaxing.
李公朴先生四天前在昆明
4 days ago in Kunming, Mr. Li Gongpu
被国民党特务杀害了
was murdered by secret agents of the KMT.
他犯了什么罪 竟遭到如此的手段
What crime has he committed to deserve such a fate?
他只不过是用笔写写文章 用嘴说说话
He used his pen and he spoke up.
他所写的所说的
Everything he wrote and said
恰恰是一个没有丢掉良心的
was precisely what any Chinese with a conscience
中国人的话
should write and speak of.
无耻啊 无耻
What a shame.
这是反动派的无耻
The counter-revolutionaries' shame
恰是李先生的光荣
is precisely Mr. Li's honor
李先生的血不会白流
His blood will not be shed in vain
李先生赔上了一个生命
Mr Li gave up his life
我们要讨回一个代价
There's a price to be paid for his life.
正义是杀不完的
Justice will prevail,
因为真理永远存在
because truth will prevail
要民主 反内战
We want democracy, not civil war.
就说我不在
Tell him I went out.
副委员长
Sir.
委员长真的不在
The Chairman is not here for real.
委员长恩赐我出洋考察
He sent me on an overseas expedition.
特来向我的义弟辞行
I came to say goodbye to my sworn brother.
他倒不在
But he's not here
副委员长 您提着个灯笼
Vice President, why the lantern?
大白天的
It's broad daylight.
大白天
Daylight?
黑暗啊
I see only darkness.
不打灯笼我找不着道
I can't see without a lantern.
冯长官 说笑话
You must be kidding, Sir.
我哪有这个心情
I'm not in the mood
三民主义吾党所宗
"The Three Principles of the People" is the cornerstone of our Party
他要再一意孤行
If he's bent on having his way,
国民党败亡之日当在不远
the days of our Party are numbered.
我就是这么句话
That's all I have to say.
请他多保重吧
Tell him to take care
张家口是共军晋察冀边区的首府
Zhangjiakou is the capital of the Shanxi-Chahar-Hebei Border Region,
也是中共手中唯一的大城市
it's also the only major city under the CPC
这里有他们重要的兵工厂
that has an arsenal that's crucial to them.
这座城市马上就要回到政府手里了
But it'll be returned to the Nationalist Government soon.
你的意思是想告诉我
General, are you saying
中共军队的军事工业基础
the manufacturing and military base of the CPC
将不复存在
doesn't exist any more?
毛泽东不认输的精神值得钦佩
I admire Mao for never giving up.
但是靠嘴皮子和拼命
But talk is cheap
是行不通的
and you can't just work your finger to the bone
实力决定一切
Power is everything.
依你的说法
According to you,
这一次中共是必定失败了
the Communist Party is doomed to fail this time?
我没有这样讲
I didn't say that
我可以和你打个赌
I'll make you a wager.
如果中共赢了
The CPC wins,
我傅作义愿意为毛泽东牵马执鞭
I'm willing to hold Mao's horsewhip.
二十年前
20 years ago,
我党为寻求和平
we surrendered our arms
放下过武器
for peace.
结果呢 换来的不是和平
What happened? We got a massacre in return,
而是大屠杀
not peace.
所以我们长了记性
We learn from our mistakes
为了实现和平
For peace,
为了未来 消灭战争
for our future and to eliminate war.
就必须对敌人强加给我们的这场战争
In this war imposed on us by our enemies,
予以反击
we must retaliate.
在本届国民代表会议闭幕之后
Within 3 months of the closing of this NPC,
政府将在三个月内
our government
勘平内乱
will put an end to this civil war.
彻底消灭叛乱割据之共产武装
We will annihilate the separatist regime by force of arms
实现国家之实质统一
to bring forth a unified country
民族之实质和平
and bring peace to our nation.
有人说 放弃延安
Some say the evacuation from Yan'an
使中国革命受到了重大挫折
marks a major setback in the Chinese Revolution.
如果这也算是挫折的话
If this is a setback,
我们这个党这支军队
our party and this army
就是在无数这样的挫折中走过来的
have survived countless setbacks.
存地失人 人地皆失
You keep the land and lose the people, you lose both.
存人失地 人地皆存
You keep the people and lose the land, you have both
我们要用一个延安 换取全中国
I'll trade Yan'an for the whole of China.
和平走了九十九步
We came all this way
就差一步
but we're still one step away from peace
要放弃 不甘心啊
What a shame to give it up
毛泽东说得对 没有手里的枪
Mao was right: Without guns in their hands,
老蒋根本不会和我们谈判
Chiang will never negotiate with us
国共谈判 我们民盟是保人
The CDL served as mediator between the KMT and CPC.
可蒋介石得寸进尺
But Chiang is insatiable.
人家中共让出了地盘
The CPC gave up their turf,
却没有换来和平
but they did not get the peace they wanted.
看来我这个保人 到头了
Some guarantor I am.
老蒋要搞一党的国大
Chiang wants a one-party NPC.
中共不参加 我们也不参加
If neither the CPC or CDL shows up,
那不是把政权送给老蒋了吗
we'll be handing the regime to him.
糊涂啊 参加了
Don't be stupid
那才是中了蒋介石的圈套
We'll fall into his trap if we show up.
我们的态度是明确的
Our position is clear.
除了联合政府 其他都是非法的
Only a coalition government is legal
没有国内和平 就没有国民大会
There'll be no NPC without peace
没有政治协商 就没有民主联合政府
and no coalition government without political consultancy.
那表老的意思是
You're saying...
和中共站在一边
We side with the CPC
蒋介石那个国大
I, Zhang Lan,
我张澜绝不参加
will not attend Chiang's NPC.
从东北局的经验来看
Based on the experience of the Northeast Bureau,
占领农村 实行土地改革
we implement land reforms in the countryside.
效果是明显的
The results are quite obvious.
让开大路 占领两厢
Stay off the main road, take the vicinity of the city,
把土地分给农民
give the land to the farmers.
使耕者有其田 天下就是我们的
We'll take over when those who plough the land can own it
后勤分队走散了
The supplies unit got separated.
吃的穿的都存在问题
We have problems with food and clothes.
老毛
Zedong.
主席
Mr. Chairman.
晚上我还要给新华社写社论
I need to write an editorial for the Xinhua News Agency.
这半根蜡烛啊 省着点儿用吧
I need the rest of this candle for later
老毛 这开书记处会呢
But we're having a meeting.
不就是开会嘛 开会就是说话
Precisely, just keep talking.
看见看不见的没关系
You don't need to see anything
这不是成了开黑会了吗
Groping in the dark?
说正事儿
Let's get back to business.
老蒋不顾一切大打出手
Chiang threw caution to the wind and declared war.
子弹不长眼
Bullets don't have eyes.
我的意见
In my opinion,
我 恩来 弼时
Enlai, Bishi and I
组成前敌委员会 留在陕北
will form a front committee and stay in Shanbei
少奇 老总组成中央工作委员会
Shaoqi, you and Zhu De form a Central Working Committee
东渡黄河去华北
and cross the Yellow River into North China.
搞两个中央
We'll work from both sides
鸡蛋不能放在一个篮子里
Don't put all your eggs in one basket.
分开摆放
Keep them separate.
打烂了一坨 还有一坨嘛
We'II still have the other when one is crushed
快 下车
Hurry. Get out
把楼里的人统统赶走
Get rid of everyone inside.
把这儿结我封了
Seal up this place
这个该死的老蒋
That son of a bitch
居然敢查封民盟总部
He had the audacity to seize the CDL headquarters
限制组织活动
and restrict our activities.
李济深 何香凝在香港
Li Jishen and He Xiangning
成立了国民党革命委员会
set up the Revolutionary Committee of the KMT in Hong Kong.
冯玉祥 蔡廷锴这些国民党元老
Founding members such as Feng Yuxiang and Cai Tingkai
纷纷响应 打明旗号要反蒋自立
have indicated their intention to break away from Chiang
国民党分裂了
The KMT is splitting up.
你也马上去香港
You should leave for Hong Kong right away
我们也要在香港重开民盟总部
We'll re-open the CDL headquarters in Hong Kong
表老 这
But...
我支持表老的意见
I'm all for it
决不能再错过这个机会了
We must not miss this chance.
现在宣布
I hereby announce
中华民国第一任总统选举结果
the results of the first presidential election of the Republic of China
下面公布计票结果
with the following votes:
蒋中正 2430票
Chiang Kai-shek 2, 430 votes;
居正 269票
Ju Zheng 269 votes.
根据中华民国宪法及其选举法
According to the constitution of the ROC and electoral law,
我宣布
I hereby announce
蒋中正先生当选中华民国第一任总统
Mr. Chiang Kai-shek is elected first President of the ROC
祝贺你
Congratulations.
祝贺
Congrats
胡宗南来电 延安丢了
Hu Zongnan wired. We lost Yan'an
蒋介石在南京当了总统
Chiang Kai-shek was elected President in Nanjing.
我毛泽东就在山沟沟里自封万岁
Long live Mao Zedong in the valley.
不好看也不好听
Nothing to brag about
口号二十三条里那个万岁必须拿掉
Get rid of the 'Iong live' in clause 23 of the slogan.
蒋介石想当皇帝 让他当
Let Chiang be the emperor.
我们不凑那个热闹
I won't join his party
另外 第五条
Clause 5,
只强调工人阶级作用的提法也不妥
mere mention of the working class is inappropriate.
我们一贯坚持政治协商联合政府
We have insisted on a coalition government
突然变了说法 不好
It's bad to sing a different tune.
我同意主席对两点意见的修改
I agree with the amendments.
那就表决吧 同意的举手
Let's have a show of hands
马上播报
Go on air with this.
新华广播电台
Xinhua Radio broadcasts
现在播报中共中央五一劳动节口号
the CPC slogan for Labor Day on May 1.
一 今年的五一劳动节
First, this year's Labor Day
是中国人民走向全国胜利的日子
is the day the Chinese people head towards victory.
二 今年的五一劳动节
Second, this year's Labor Day
是中国人民的死敌蒋介石
is the day the Chinese people's enemy Chiang Kai-shek
走向灭亡的日子
meets his doom.
五 各民主党派 各人民团体
Fifth, all democratic parties and organizations
各社会贤达迅速召开政治协商会议
should immediately call for the CPPCC
讨论并实现召集人民代表大会
to discuss and elect delegates
成立民主联合政府
to set up a coalition government.
中共下了一步好棋
The CPC made an excellent move
下棋您是高手
You're the chess expert.
这一回可不能举棋不定
This time you must make up your mind.
话是这么说的 至于做嘛
It's easier said than done.
还得看中共下一步的走法
It'll depend on the CPC's next move
我听说李宗仁来信请您回南京
I heard Li Zongren had invited you to Nanjing.
老蒋那边也在拉您
Chiang wants you too.
李宗仁
Li Zongren.
孙科
Sun Ke
李宗仁
Li Zongren.
文人来做总统
If the President is a litearati,
你做副总统我没有意见
I don't mind if you become Vice President
总统是个军人
But the President is already a soldier
副总统再由军人来做就不合适了
The Vice President should not be another soldier.
别人会说我们是军政府了
People will say this is a military government
本来总统发话 我不该再坚持
Normally, I won't insist if you say so.
不过 从选举到现在
But since the election,
寄托的不再是我宗仁一人的心血
more than my effort is at stake.
不是我不想退
Not that I don't want to step down,
实在是不能再退了
I simply can't.
党内不支持你
Without support from the Party,
即便参选也选不上
you won't be elected.
何苦成为中外的笑柄呢
Why be a laughing stock?
这就要唯公议是从
Let the numbers speak for themselves.
说不定能选上
Maybe I'll win.
你一定选不上
Definitely not.
孙科 1295票
Sun Ke 1, 295 votes.
李宗仁 1438票
Li Zongren 1, 438 votes.
根据中华民国宪法及其选举法
According to the constitution of the ROC and electoral law,
我宣布李宗仁先生
I hereby announce, Mr. Li Zongren
当选中华民国副总统
is elected Vice President of the ROC.
余谨以至诚
I
向全国人民宣誓
do solemnly swear...
这北平 我有好几年没来了
I haven't been to Beiping in years.
华北剿总总司令
Commander-in-Chief of North China.
管五个省 好几十万人
5 provinces and a few hundred thousand people under your command.
您裂土封王了
You're the king
你这丫头挖苦我
Don't make fun of me.
这是蒋委员长器重您
Mr. Chiang has high regard for you.
新政协要是能把
If the new CPPCC
这名单上的高人都请来
can invite half the people on this list,
就成功了一半
we're half way there.
是啊
You're right.
你最好亲自给冯玉祥将军写封信
You better write to General Feng personally.
嗯 我现在就写
I'll do that right now.
主席 该吃饭了
Mr Chairman, time to eat
恩来啊 一起吃吧
Please join me, Enlai.
不 我还要赶回西拍坡
No, I must get back to Xibaipo.
吃完了再走嘛
Finish eating first
那好
Very well.
主席
Mr. Chairman,
做饭的郭师傅是小阎的老乡
the cook is Xiao Yan's old lad
他想见见您
He wants to see you
吃人家东西嘴短 要见的
Of course
谢谢主席
Thank you, sir.
快来快来
Hurry.
报告主席 他叫郭本财 是俺老乡
His name is Guo Bencai. He's from my hometown.
主席好
Hello, Mr. Chairman.
郭师傅 你这个饭菜做得好啊
Mr. Kwok, you're a good cook.
结主席做饭 我这辈子都值了
It's worth everything to cook for you
来 抽根烟
Have a smoke
谢谢主席
Thank you, sir.
嗯 你这是
Why...
主席的烟 我不舍得抽
It's your cigarette, I want to keep it.
拿着
Take this.
使不得 使不得
I can't.
哎 拿着抽吧
Take it.
谢谢主席
主席 这是军区小灶司务长 刘从文
Sir, this is Liu Congwen, the mess officer in the military zone.
毛主席好
Hello, sir.
你好啊
Hello.
周副主席好
Hello, Mr. Zhou.
你好 郭师傅好
Hello. Mr Kwok.
你好
Hello.
毛主席对饭菜还有什么要求
Mr. Chairman, any special requests for your meals?
我们一定全力满足
We'II do the best we can.
我的要求不高
I don't need much.
只要顿顿放辣椒
Make sure we put in chili.
给您备着呢
I prepared for you already.
当然了 要是隔个十天半月
It'd be perfect
能吃上一顿红烧肉 那就更好了
if I can have stewed meat twice a month.
大鱼在城南庄
Big fish in Chengnanzhuang
村北近山两棵杏树之间平房内
In a bungalow between 2 apricot trees near the mountains in the northern part of the village
校长 照您的吩咐
Per your request,
南京 上海 香港行动小组的人
field operation units
都撒了下去
in Nanjing, Shanghai and Hong Kong have been removed.
张澜困居上海 要予以控制
Zhang Lan is stuck in Shanghai. Keep him under tabs.
是
Yes, sir
李济深他在香港
Li Jishen is in Hong Kong
那边不是我们的地盘 盯紧就是了
He's not on our turf. Just keep an eye on him.
是
Yes, sir
可是我的这位大哥冯玉祥
As for Feng Yuxiang,
最近和中共走得很近
he's getting tight with the CPC.
要防止他投共变节
He may defect
必要的时候 个别人
If necessary,
我看能不能清理一下
I'll tidy things up a bit
都是些有声望的人
These are prestigious men
你做的不干净
If you're sloppy,
国际舆论对我们很不利
public opinion overseas will backfire on us
卑职明白
I understand
毛泽东的行踪可以确定了吗
Mao's location is confirmed?
保定 城南庄
Chengnanzhuang in Baoding.
这次他跑不了
He won't get away this time.
好 记住 这是大事
Remember, this is extremely important.
报告报告 确认目标
Confirm target, roger
哎 老郭 你上哪去 这边
Lao Guo, where are you going? This way.
回厨房 锅里给毛主席炖着菜呢
Back to the kitchen. Chairman Mao's food is on the stove
主席 主席呢
Chairman?
主席吃了安眠药 刚睡下
He took some sleeping pills and went to sleep.
赶快叫醒 敌机马上就到
Wake him up. Enemy planes will be here soon.
小虎 跟我拿担架去
Tiger, get a stretcher.
是
快醒醒 主席 有敌机
Wake up, sir. Enemy planes are coming.
不是还没扔炸弹嘛
They haven't dropped a bomb.
扔下来就晚了
Then it'll be too late.
走啊 主席
Let's go, sir
慌什么
Calm down.
烟
Cigarette.
不能再抽了
Do that later.
聂司令
Commander Nie.
把主席指上担架 去防空洞
Move Mr. Chairman to the bomb shelter on the stretcher
是
Yes, sir
就是扔炸弹
Even if they start bombing,
也不见得就能炸着我毛泽东
that doesn't mean they'll hit me
我得向中央负责
I'm responsible for the Party
我命大着呢
I'm very lucky.
快
Hurry.
快 快点儿
快
Hurry.
快跑 快啊
喂喂 喂
Hello...
怎么样
Well?
还是要不通
Still can't get through.
继续要
Keep trying.
是
Yes, sir
周副主席 电报来了
Telegram, sir.
遭到敌机轰炸 伤亡情况不明
Massive bombings, casualties unknown.
敌机轰炸的时候
The food was still on the stove
锅里还炖着菜
when the bombing started.
老郭想到主席还没吃早餐
Lao Guo said you have not eaten breakfast
就又跑回去了
He ran back to the kitchen
周副主席 电报
Telegram, Mr. Zhou
主席
Mr. Chairman,
五一节口号有了广泛的回应
we have very positive response for the May 1 slogan.
众党派都具名签字了
The Parties have all signed their names.
哦 这么快啊
Already?
这倒是始料未及啊
What a surprise.
是啊 现在各方态度已经明朗
The situation is becoming clear
民盟和民革都站到我们一边
The CDL and the Revolutionary Committee are on our side.
老蒋彻底孤立了
Chiang is now completely isolated.
水到渠成 召开新政协这件大事
Everything will fall into place
该做出安排了
It's time to call for a new CPPCC.
任公 毛泽东写了亲笔信给你
Jishen, Mao wrote you personally.
还顾虑什么
What's your concern?
当初在福建 相约一道反蒋
Back in Fujian, we agreed to oppose Chiang.
可他们变了卦
But they changed their minds
福建的事情已经过去数年了
Fujian was a few years ago.
再说 那是博古 不是毛泽东
That was Bo Gu, not Mao.
我不是记仇
I'm not holding a grudge.
实在是跌跟头跌怕了
I don't need another fall
老蒋拿我们玩了几十年
Chiang toyed with us for decades
中共虽然这些年信誉很好
No doubt the CPC has better credibility,
可万一
but what if...
旗号刚立起来
We just set up a new Party.
我既然坐在了民革主席这个位置上
As the Chairman of Revolutionary Committee of the KMT,
那就得为民革的前途和命运
I must do my best
尽心尽力
for the future of the Party
我们先单独发表一份声明
Issue a separate declaration
以反蒋的名义
to oppose Chiang
重申我们反对一党独裁的宗旨
Reiterate our opposition against one-party autocracy.
就算对中共一个回应
That'll be our response to the CPC.
目前在关内
Nowhere inside the Shanhai Pass
我们还没有重开政协合适的地方
is a suitable venue for the new consultative meeting,
只能选在哈尔滨
except Harbin
远是远了点儿
It's far away,
可毕竟是座大城市
but at least it's a big city.
冯玉祥这个月启程回国
Feng Yuxiang will be home this month
他也会直接去东北
He'll go directly to the Northeast.
那就暂定哈尔滨吧
Then let's settle for Harbin.
要组建全国政府啊
To build a new government for the whole country
手里没有几个像样的大城市
without a decent big city,
总是捉襟见肘
it's just not adequate
商品稀缺 货物流入黑市
Goods are scarce. Commodities entered the black market.
都在买空卖空
Everyone is buying
商人还好
and selling short
最难的是那些军政要员
The top brass in the military and political circles
有了他们的撑腰
are behind these activities.
那些投机的商人
Those profiteers
根本不把政府的命令放在眼里
defy government orders.
翁院长那边快撑不下去了
Mr. Weng can't hold the fort much longer.
办法呢
What's your solution?
我不要听你诉苦
I don't want your complaints.
我要听你的办法
I want a solution.
上海是关键
As the financial center in the Far East,
上海是远东的金融中心
Shanghai is the key.
只要上海的市场能够稳定
If we can stabilize the market in Shanghai,
全国的市场就能够稳定
the rest of the country will fall in line.
我要去上海
I must go to Shanghai.
大公子 上海各界委托我
Master Chiang, on behalf of Shanghai,
在锦江饭店为您的到来摆席接风
we're hosting a banquet for you at the Jinjiang Hotel.
一会儿我来接您
I'll pick you up later
话通知戡乱建国总队所有人
Tell everyone on the Special Commando Unit
半个小时之后到我的办公室开会
to meet in my office in half an hour,
还有你
including you
在新的政协会议的筹备事宜中
In preparing for the new CPPCC,
中共愿与我们商讨
the CPC is open for suggestions.
并无一党包办之意
They don't intend to run the whole show.
他们做事 与南京政府不同
They do things differently from the Nanjing government
张澜这边什么意见
What about Zhang Lan?
表老历来主张政治协商联合建国
He's always for building the state via CPPCC
那边已经准备了周密的计划
They already have a well thought-out plan
接您经香港和我妈妈一起北上
to escort you and my mother up north.
毛泽东请您跟李济深共同北上
Mao invited you and Li Jishen up north
参与筹备重开政协的大计
to discuss re-opening the CPPCC.
那李济深何时动身
When is Li Jishen leaving?
还没有定
Don't know yet
您看如何答复
What's your answer?
我决定
I have decided
不动
to stay put
那我们
But...
就派沈钧儒代表民盟与中共先期接洽
Let Shen Junru liaise with the CPC on behalf of the CDL
那表老准备何时北上呢
When are you leaving?
我已是古稀之年 身体又多病
I'm too old and sick.
再说 老蒋也轻易不会让我挪动
Besides, Chiang won't let me go that easily.
表老 这么大的事情 您不出面
How can you not show for something this important?
沈钧儒可以全权做主
I'm putting Shen Junru in charge.
我是中国人
I am Chinese.
爸爸 对吗
Is that right, Father?
这国字少了一点
One stroke is missing.
毛伯伯你看好看吗
Isn't this pretty, Uncle Mao?
好看 不过不是野菜 不能吃啊
Yes, but you can't eat everything.
主席 开会了
Mr. Chairman, it's time for the meeting.
好 回家喽
Let's go back
毛伯伯你背我
Will you carry me, Uncle Mao?
爸爸你背我
Carry me, Father.
毛伯伯你背我 爸爸
Will you carry me, Uncle Mao? Father
莉娅 周叔叔背你好吗
Liya, do you want me to carry you?
好啊
Yes.
走
Let's go.
恩来啊有什么最新消息啊
Any news, Enlai?
据情报 蒋介石的经济整顿陷入僵局
Chiang's economic reform is a deadlock.
蒋经国亲赴上海进行督导
Chiang Ching-kuo personally flew to Shanghai.
上海滩各种势力虎踞龙盘
But the Bund is entrenched with powerful factions.
国民党内部错综复杂
It's a labyrinth within the KMT.
老蒋做不到的 小蒋也做不到
Chiang's son won't accomplish anything.
莉娅 咱们骑大马好不好
Liya, let's play piggyback.
好啊
Yes.
走了
Let's go.
任何人都不要怀疑
No one should doubt the Government's
政府改革金融体系的决心
determination to implement financial reforms.
国难当头
In face of a national crisis,
谁在这件事情上损害了国家的利益
anyone who compromises the nation's interest
谁就是卖国贼
is a traitor
谁就是我党国的敌人
and an enemy of the KMT
还话各位前辈 工商界翘楚
I urge the elite of the business sector
以及社会贤达积极配合
and prominent individuals of society to work with us
以期能够尽快的稳定
to restore financial order and stabilize prices
金融秩序和物价水平
in the shortest time possible
为戡乱救国尽职尽力啊
and do your best to save our country.
请问蒋先生
Mr. Chiang
此次管制能否做到公平公正
Will you be fair?
对那些背景深厚的违法者
What about those offenders who have influence?
你怎么去管制
How will you handle them?
经国此番来
My mission in Shanghai
只打老虎 不拍苍蝇
is to hunt tigers, not squat mosquitoes.
蒋先生能透露一下
Mr. Chiang, can you tell us
这次的具体做法
your concrete course of action?
老虎好打
Tigers are easy to hunt
冰山 只怕小蒋先生
but I'm afraid icebergs
搬不动吧
are hard to remove.
这位先生是
You are...
恒社杜月笙
Du Yuesheng
杜先生 商界前辈 还望不吝指教
Mr. Du, I'm all ears
犬子维屏 让督导专员抓了
My son Weiping has been arrested
他犯国法 我无话可说
If he broke the law, I have no complaints,
可是如今这上海滩另有一家商号
but someone else in Shanghai
大肆囤积物资哄抬物价
is hoarding supplies
向黑市兜售
and peddling them to the black market for profits,
无视政府法令
openly defying the law
督导专员若是不管
If you choose to overlook this,
恐怕有负蒋总统一片苦心啊
President Chiang will be very disappointed.
请杜先生指出来
Please point me in the right direction, Mr. Du.
经国必定给先生一个交代
I will look into it.
念
Read it.
外滩货场辰字号七大仓库
7 godowns along the Bund.
南京路三十六号仓库
The godown on No. 36 Nanjing Road.
霞飞路十七号中美友好商社仓库
No 17 Avenue Joffre.
南市场甲字头十二间仓库
12 godowns in the South Market using the word "Jia"
大公子
Mr. Chiang,
这才是真老虎
this is the real tiger.
是谁
Who is it?
扬子公司 孔家
Yangtze Company owned by the Kung's.
给卫立煌发电报 敦促他立即南撒关内
Wire Wei Lihuang, urge him to pull back south.
有这支精兵在手里
With crack troops like these,
东北就是丢了 我们也能把它夺回来
even if we lose the Northeast, we can get it back easily.
总统 国防部已经给卫立煌发了数封电报
President, we wired him several times
敦促他南撤
urging him to go south,
但是他置若罔闻
but he ignored us.
给我准备专机
Get my plane ready,
我要立即飞往沈阳
I'II fly out to Shenyang
是
Yes.
总统到
The President
什么事
What is it?
冯玉祥 死了
Feng Yuxiang is dead.
主席
Chairman.
你们 你们平时的能耐哪里去了
What happened to you?
自吹自擂是老地下党 能耐大得很
You bragged about your abilities.
当年在上海如何如何
You bragged about Shanghai.
在红队如何如何 现在呢
You bragged about the Red Army. And now?
冯将军一个大活人 被活活烧死
General Feng was burned to death.
你们
You.
这就是你们的工作成绩
This is all you can do
必须作出检讨 一个都别想跑掉
Think it over. You won't get away.
战场上打了败仗要撤职杀头
You'll be executed if you lose a battle.
现在你们这条战线上出了问题
Now something went wrong on your front.
你们自己说该怎么办 说啊
Tell me what you should do. Speak up.
是国民党特务干的吗
KMT secret agents did it?
苏联方面解释说
According to the Russians,
是冯将军自己在船舱看电影
General Feng was watching a film in his cabin.
胶片起火 引燃了船舱
The film caught on fire and ignited the cabin.
胶片起火 他是个大活人
The film caught on fire? He's a general.
他不会跑吗
Why didn't he run?
你们怎么判断的 都是猪脑子
What a bunch of morons.
人死了 苏联方面当然要推卸责任
A man is dead, the Russians need to blame someone.
茫茫大海 又是在国外
The ship was out at sea and abroad.
一时谁也说不清楚
We didn't get all the facts
冯将军十二岁从军
General Feng became a soldier at 12.
五十年戎马生涯 身经百战而不死
50 years in the battlefield didn't kill him
却因为我们的邀请
But our invitation
万里赴会 葬身大海
to send him abroad buried him at sea
我很愧疚啊
I feel so guilty
是啊 冯将军虽然去了
General Feng may be dead
但他留下了建立一个民主独立
but he left behind a legacy
新中国的向往
to build a new, independent China.
恩来 给冯将军的夫人李德全发个唁电
Enlai, wire our condolences to Madame Feng
并恳请她参加政协会议
and invite her to the CPPCC.
好
Yes.
主席 有部分政协人士提出一个建议
Mr. Chairman, it has been suggested
由新政协代理全国人民代表大会
that the CPPCC should act for the NPC
直接选举中央人民政府
to elect the central government
战争情况下 很难做到公民普选
A general election is hard to come by during the war
但是这件事情必须先征求各党派的意见
We must consult all the other Parties on this
三步并作两步走
Let's not waste any time.
先组成联合政府 再召开人民代表会议
Form the coalition government first, then call the NPC,
是这个意思吧
is that it?
正是
Precisely
人家那边还在打仗
They're still in a war
从全国选代表还没有条件
They can't elect their delegates
应该体谅
We should make allowances for that.
好 我马上给沈均儒带话
I'll get in touch with Shen Junru
转达表老的意思
and pass on your message.
还有 毛周二公再次请表老北上
Mr. Mao and Mr. Zhou invited you up north again
集合
Assemble.
快点
Hurry.
扬子公司和孔家在上海滩的所有的仓库
Search all the godowns, buildings, apartments and villas
大楼 公寓 别墅 一个都不能漏掉
in Shanghai owned by Yangtze Company and the Kung's.
明天上午七点同时行动 明白吗
Operation starts at 7 am tomorrow morning, understand?
主席先生
Mr. Chairman.
美国的政府人士表示愿意支持李先生
Voices within the US government have indicated
取代蒋先生的位置
they will support your replacement of Mr. Chiang.
不知您对这个问题有什么看法
What do you think?
美国人支持老夫也好 支持老蒋也罢
Whether they support me or Chiang,
都不过是以华制华的把戏
it's a cheap trick to pit Chinese against Chinese
美国想要和未来的中国打交道
If the US wishes to maintain diplomatic relations with the future China,
而无视中共的存在
ignoring the CPC
那是掩耳盗铃
is unrealistic.
第二个问题
The second question.
如果李副总统取代蒋总统执政
If Vice President Li replaced President Chiang,
您认为局势会有所好转吗
will things get better?
若讲用兵
In terms of warfare,
白崇禧这个小诸葛还算有点儿真本事
Bai Chongxi is quite capable.
若讲权术
In terms of politics,
李宗仁白崇禧加起来都不是老蒋的对手
Li Zongren and Bai Chongxi together are no match for Chiang.
主席先生 您好橡没有回答我的问题
You did not answer my question, sir.
老总
Here
主席 看什么呐
What are you looking at?
锦州
Jinzhou.
隔着一千多公里
That's over 1,000 km away.
确切的消息最快要明天才能过来
More definite news won't arrive until tomorrow.
十点半还没突进去的是哪个部队啊
It's already 10:30 and yet no sign of attack. Which division was it?
八纵 这个问题
The 8th column.
你都问了五遍了
You asked me 5 times already
是吗
Really?
锦州一战 非一城一地之争啊
The Battle of Jinzhou is not just over a city or a region
打赢了 满盘皆活
If we win, we can go on
打不下去 局势就变复杂了
If we lose, the situation gets complicated
政协会议的草案 张澜 沈钧儒回信了
With regards to the draft agenda of the CPPCC,
表示赞同 有一些小的修改 均是细节
Zhang Lan and Shen Junru made minor changes
够朋友 他们知道我们在打仗
They know we're at war.
能理解 难得啊
They're being very understanding.
表老生病了
Zhang Lan is sick.
北上的事 可能得缓一缓
We should postpone his trip up north
将心比心 请 一定要请
We must invite him.
至于什么时候来
But we'll let him decide
由表老自己决定吧
when to come.
我们等
We'll wait.
姨妈 人家大权在握
Aunt, he has full authority
一句话就把我扬子公司里里外外全都封了
to seize everything owned by the Yangtze Company
还派人满上海滩的传讯我
He put out word all over Shanghai looking for me
也好 今天见了面
Now I finally see him.
也省的大表哥大费周章了
That ought to save him some trouble.
戴维 你疯了
Have you gone mad, David?
姨妈放心 人家是督导专员 是太子
Relax. He's the Liaison Administrator, the prince.
我哪里敢拿枪打太子
I wouldn't dare shoot the prince.
大表哥 这个事情很简单
This is very simple, cousin.
你一枪把我打死 就都了结了
Shoot me and it's all over
罪犯伏法 蒋青天誉满沪上
With the culprit dead, you'll be famous in Shanghai.
咱们也算各得其所了
We'll both get what we want.
经国
Ching-kuo.
督导专署的公文说的很清楚
It's clearly written in the state papers.
限你十日之内去接受询问
You're needed for questioning within 10 days
否则严惩不贷
or you'll be severely punished.
已经过了七天了 你自己看着办
7 days have gone by, you decide what to do next
扬子公司都是孔家的产业
Yangtze Company is our family estate.
你有本事把我父亲也抓了
I dare you to arrest my father.
胡说八道 明明自己做错了事
Nonsense. It's clearly your fault
还把你父亲扯进来
Leave your father out of this
你父亲和大姐要是知道你这么胡闹
If he and Ai-ling found out about your monkey business,
饶不了你
they won't spare you
上海滩里里外外做了多少年
This is how we do business in Shanghai.
来了个督导专员就变天了
But the arrival of a Liaison Administrator changed all that
姨妈 大家都这么做 这就是行业规矩
Auntie, everyone does it. That's the rule
做生意不讲究行业规矩
Only a feudalistic dictator
那是封建独裁者的做法
would run a business without rules.
你说谁是独裁者
Who are you calling a dictator?
政府戡乱 将士们在前线流血
The government is fighting a war and soldiers are dying on the front
国库却拿不出钱来 还要向美国去贷款
But the state treasury is empty and we had to borrow from the Americans.
货币贬值 物价飞涨
Currency has depreciated and prices have skyrocketed.
黎民百姓人心惶惶
People are running scared.
而孔总经理你的仓库里面
But inside your godowns,
却囤积着数以万吨计的物资
you hoarded over 100 thousand tons of supplies
不愿意出售
which you are unwilling to sell.
我是商人 不是慈善家
I'm a businessman, not a philanthropist
中共已经在搞土地改革和政治协商了
The CPC is working on land reforms and political consultation.
连蔡廷锴跟沈钧儒都去了东北
Even Cai Tingkai and Shen Junru have left for the Northeast.
毛泽东要另立政府跟中央政府分庭抗礼了
Mao is setting up his own government.
夫人 您是最支持父亲的
Madame, you've always supported Father.
可是您万万没有想到吧
I bet you never expected
在这里 就是在这里
right here in Shanghai,
有的人在挖父亲的墙角
someone is undermining him,
在摧毁这个国家的根基
destroying the foundation of this country.
他们的财富 他们的公寓
Their fortune, apartments,
大衣 香水 冰箱 都像有毒的病菌
clothes, perfumes and iceboxes are like a virus
寄生在瘦骨如柴的国家身上
residing on the mere skeleton of this country.
他们才是国家的敌人 是我父亲的敌人
They are the enemy, Father's and the state's
够了
That's enough,
经国
Ching-kuo.
这里没有敌人 只有家人
There are no enemies here, only family.
今天我们不谈国事 只谈家事
Let's talk about family today.
不在其局 不谋其政
I'm not in the position to say anything
现在的国防部长是何应钦
He Yingqin is the Director of National Defense
扶危定难 让老蒋找他吧
Take pains to stay save. Let Chiang talk to him.
何应钦的枪法没有你这么精准
You're a better marksman than He Yingqin.
枪法好有什么用
So what?
现在的中国都是蒋家的
Chiang owns China now.
你看看 这枪上都刻着蒋中正的名字
Even this gun has his name engraved on it
我辈又能奈何
What can we do about it?
这中正式步枪 共军里有很多士兵在用
The CPC troops use this type of rifle too.
关键不在于枪上写的什么名字
What matters is not the name on the rifle,
而在于拿枪的人
but the man who uses it
手里握着枪
Holding a rifle
总比握着个国防部长的空名头要有用
beats holding an empty title of Director of National Defense
如果你做了总统
If you're the President,
美国人还会支持我们吗
will the Americans back us up?
司徒大使做过这方面的暗示
Stuart dropped a hint.
那我们就把老蒋赶下台
Then let's get rid of Chiang.
此语 言之尚早
It's still too early to say.
不过末雨绸缪
Never too early to take precautions.
也应该着手准备了
It's time we get started
经儿 夫人明天就要去美国了
Ching-kuo, Madam is leaving for the US tomorrow
是去请求杜鲁门总统援助的
to ask President Truman for help.
东北的局面急剧恶化
The situation in the Northeast is deteriorating quickly.
我们需要美国的支持啊
We need help from the Americans
我专程从东北飞回来
I flew back from the Northeast
就是想告诉你
just to tell you,
在这个时候
at a time like this
后院不能起火
we can't afford a fire in the backyard.
父亲
Father
如果不严惩孔家 昭示天下
If we don't punish the Kung's,
上海的经济就全垮了
the economy in Shanghai is doomed.
你说的我全明白
I absolutely understand
国民党的腐败已经到了骨头里了
The corruption of the KMT is in the bones.
这不是一个孔家的问题
It's not just the problem of the Kung's
反贪腐是件大事
Crackdown on corruption is a major issue
要讲求时机 讲求分寸
Timing and extent are crucial...
难呐
it's tough.
反 要亡党
You lose the Party if you proceed.
不反 亡国
You lose the country if you don't.
难
It's tough.
父亲
Father
党 国 都已经在危难的边缘了
Both the Party and the country are on the brink of disaster.
好了
Alright
当前最大的事情
The matter at hand
是把北方的军队撤到长江以南
is to move the troops up North to south of the Yangtze River
确保江南的稳定
to ensure the safety there
这个时候追究孔家
Going after the Kung's
已经没有什么意义了
is meaningless now.
表老这个川北圣人 那是真圣人
Zhang Lan is truly a saint of Sichuan.
不是虚的
He deserves it.
政治协商会议若是没有他在
Without him at the CPPCC,
恐怕我们这些四川老乡
none of us Sichuanese
没有一个人敢去啊
would dare to go.
表老年纪太大 东北又天寒地冻
The Northeast is too cold for a man his age.
老人家确实来不了
He probably can't make it
万一有个三长两短
If anything happens to him...
北平如何
What about Beiping?
什么
What?
把会期延迟到明年
Postpone the meeting till next year.
地点就改在北平
Move the venue to Beiping
我看要得
It's possible.
可是 东野刚刚占领沈阳 部队很疲劳
The troops are tired after taking Shenyang.
傅作义有六十多万人马
Fu Zuoyi commands 600,000 men.
仅靠晋察冀两个兵团
Relying on 2 divisions in the Shanxi-Chahar-Hebei Border Region
想在短期内占领北平 不可能啊
to capture Beiping is impossible.
北平城工部消息
According to our intelligence
傅作义最近思想起伏很大
lately, Fu Zuoyi is having second thoughts.
偷袭石家庄失败以后
After the failed attempt on Shijiazhuang,
他似乎有和我们谈判的意向
he seems willing to negotiate
赶紧派可靠的人与傅作义联系
Send someone reliable to liaise with him.
好
Ok.
北平若能和平解放 善莫大焉
It'd be heavenly, if we can liberate Beiping peacefully.
傅的女儿傅冬菊是我党党员
Fu's daughter Dongju is a Party member.
联系人她最合适
She's perfect for the job
是啊
Yes.
大局如此 我就独裁专断一回
In that case, I'll be the dictator for a change.
要求东野 于七日内动身入关
Ask the Northeast Field Army to enter the Shanhai Pass within 7 days.
告诉林彪
Tell Lin Biao
这不是探讨 而是命令
this is an order and not a probe.
部队的收拢集结 需要几天的时间
It'll take a few days to gather up the troops
各纵队的解放团都还没有来得及消化
and each column needs time to adjust otherwise.
就这么入关恐怕要出问题
Moving inside the Pass will be a problem.
还有 关外的战士干部他们不愿意入关
The cadres don't want to make the move
做动员工作还需要点儿时间
and it'll take time for deployment.
这二十二日的最后期限太紧了
The deadline on the 22nd is too tight.
复电军委 十八日十八时来电敬悉
Wire this back: Received order dispatched on 18th at 18:00
我们决遵来电于二十二日出发
Will set out on the 22nd as instructed.
详细部署另电告 林罗刘
Details to follow Signed, Lin, Luo & Liu
您自己也得早作打算了
You should think for yourself too.
你这丫头还真想要我去
You really want me
给你们那位主席牵马执鞭啊
to hold the horsewhip for your Chairman?
爸 一句玩笑话 您别老放在心上
Forget it, Father It was a joke.
玩笑话
A joke?
那是我亲口对美国记者说的
I personally told the American reporter.
那就不是玩笑话了
It's not a joke.
那是您自己想不开
That's because you took it to heart
李济深是党国的元老 反蒋也出了名的
Li Jishen is a founding member of the Party who opposes Chiang openly
最近这几个月
Over these last few months,
毛泽东几次请他北上共商大计
Mao has repeatedly invited him up north.
他一直拖着 他也想不开
He's been stalling him. He's bewildered by
你来看我
You come to see me
带了张十八年前的旧报纸
with a 18-year old newspaper.
用心良苦啊
How kind of you.
您跟总统之间的恩怨
The quarrel between you and the President
那是本党自己的事
should stay within the Party.
您跟共产党之间
Between you and the CPC,
您别忘了 当年广州杀了他们多少人
don't forget you ordered the execution of Cai Hesen.
你想说什么
What are you saying?
跟我回南京 行政院立法院随您挑
Return to Nanjing and pick any job you want,
只要不投共 就行
as long as you don't join the CPC
封官许愿
A promotion for a promise?
你说 我会去吗
You think I'll go?
任公 临来的时候副总统已经交代了
Before I came, Vice President Li told me
希望通过您与共党进行沟通
he would like to liaise with the CPC through you.
至于条件嘛 无不可谈
Any condition is negotiable,
就是划江而治 也不是不行
including using the Yangtze as a partition.
划江而治
Use the Yangtze as a partition
这是分裂中国
and split up China?
你告诉李宗仁
Tell Li Zongren
这个千古骂名 他背不起
The infamy is more than he can handle.
总统好
Hello, Mr President
傅总司令
Commander Fu.
我们的军队可以收缩到塘沽到张家口一线
Our troops can pull back to Tanggu and Zhangjiakou
进攻不敢言胜
I can't guarantee we'll win
防守 万无一失
But we're perfectly capable of defense.
从全局出发
With the big picture in mind.
我打算把华北的六十万人马调往江南
I intend to move 600,000 men to Jiangnan
这样 进可攻退可守
I can be more flexible in both defense and offense
退居东南是偏安
That's containing our sovereignty to the southeast.
北平乃民国故都 政治地位显要
As the old capital, Beiping has political significance.
轻易放弃
Giving it up
在国际观瞻上对政府大不利啊
is unfavorable to our government internationally
说的是啊 国际观瞻 是大局
You're right. International scope is the situation.
你等一等
Wait.
爸 有事啊
What is it, Father?
你现在的上级领导是谁啊
Who's your commanding officer?
我们不是说过 互不过问嘛
We agreed not to discuss that
我想和那边的人谈一谈
I wish to talk to them.
谈什么 谈牵马执鞭啊
About what? The horsewhip?
冬菊 我现在和你说的话
What I'm telling you now
关系到近百万人的生死
will determine the lives of millions.
我知道了
I understand
她真是太迷人了
She's so hot.
很抱歉 夫人
I'm sorry, May-ling.
白宫和国会
Both the House and the Congress
都拒绝了您的演讲请求
have refused your request to make another speech.
当然美国还会一如既往地支持蒋先生
But the Government will still support the General as before
只是不希望中国内战继续下去
with the hope that the civil war does not continue any longer in China.
杜鲁门总统及美国政府如今的重心在欧洲
President Truman and his administration is concentrating on Europe.
可是东方 同样需要复兴
But the East needs a revival too.
我的朋友
My friend.
您的方案本来就应该包括中国的
China should have been included in your plan.
美国的援助和贷款
Any loans and assistance from the US now
必须保证被用于和平的建设活动
should be spent on security and constructive activities,
而不是战争
not war
原先签订的四亿美元贷款协议仍然有效
You got 400 million dollars from the original loan.
那笔贷款现在
That's still in existence.
仅剩几百万美元的额度了
We both know there's only a few million dollars left.
这不足以拯救我丈夫的政府
And it's not enough to support my husband's administration
和他毕生的事业
and his life's work.
国务卿先生
Mr. Secretary of State,
我们需要新的援助
we need your additional assistance,
我恳请您了
please.
夫人 对此我们无能为力
Madam, there's nothing more we can do.
元旦快到了
New Year is coming up.
侍从室拟一个公告 月底发布吧
Make this announcement at month end.
什么内容
About what?
他们要我下台 我便下台吧
If they want me to resign, I'll resign.
总统 万万不可
You can't do that, Mr. President.
不是我想引退
It's not my choice.
是我们党内的某些人要赶我走
But someone within our Party wants me out.
毛泽东周恩来几番邀请被你回绝
You repeatedly rejected Mao and Zhou's invitation.
你的架子好大哦
You're too arrogant.
廖夫人言重了
That's an overstatement, Madame Liao.
一则是家里的确有事
I'm tied up at home
二来军事组公务走不开 所以
And I'm also busy with military affairs
新政协筹备一日紧似一日
Preparations for the new CPPCC are moving along and days are counting.
国民党几十年了 总不能缺席吧
After decades, the KMT can't be absent
您迟疑着不肯去
You're still hesitant about going.
难道要毛泽东到南京去请蒋介石吗
You expect Mao to fly to Nanjing to invite Chiang?
蒋介石我们是绝对不会请的
We're definitely not inviting him.
他是战犯是元凶嘛
He's a war criminal, a murderer.
开政治协商会议 没有国民党不行
We can't have a CPPCC without the KMT.
任公啊 毛主席说了
Jishen, Chairman Mao said
他在北平等您
he'd wait for you in Beiping.
报告团长 前面有个地主大院
Chief, some landlord's compound up ahead
院墙太高 爬不上去
The wall is too high for us to climb over.
手榴弹都炸不开 请炮兵支援吧
Grenades won't blow it apart. Please send for the artillery.
照明弹
Flare
报告司令员 报告司令员
Commander...
突击团己到达北平城下
we have reached Beiping city
主席 两个好消息
2 pieces of good news, sir
第一个
First,
李济深和沈雁冰 章乃器先生一道
Li Jishen, Shen Yanbing and Zhang Naiqi
四天前就起程了
left 4 days ago.
乘坐阿尔丹号货轮 后天在大连上岸
They boarded the Aldan and will disembark at Dalian day after tomorrow.
好啊 那第二个呢
And the other one?
蒋介石下台了
Chiang Kai-shek resigned
大使先生
Mr. Ambassador.
作为中国政府的盟友
As China's ally,
美国此时此刻为什么要袖手旁观呢
why is the US doing nothing at a time like this?
上帝帮助自助者 我的朋友
God help those who help themselves, my friend
我看 蒋介石是在给李宗仁出难题
I think Chiang is giving Li Zongren a hard time.
知道李宗仁想和谈 他便抢先提出来
He knows Li wants to negotiate, so he brought it up first.
一来是怕李宗仁抢了开启和谈的美名
He doesn't want Li to get the credit
二来 也想恶心我们一下
and he wants to give us a hard time.
老蒋 下台就下台 偏要摆个姿态
He already stepped down, but he had to pull a stunt like this.
这么一弄
After this,
李宗仁再想和我们谈就困难重重了
it would be tough for Li to talk to us.
现在民盟和民革等各方面
The CDL and the other Parties
都还没有表态 还都在看着
have yet to make a stand, they're waiting to see.
不过我估计
In my opinion,
他们从心里上
deep down
还是希望我们能够谈一谈的
they want us to talk.
李宗仁想要和平 我们想要和平
Li Zongren wants peace, we want peace,
第三方也想要和平
the other Parties want peace.
既然如此 就给李代总统个面子
We'll do the Acting President a favor
好啊
Great.
那我们就给他一次和平谈判的机会
Let's give him a chance to talk,
但是怎么谈 那得我们说了算
but we decide how.
捷报 捷报
Victory bulletin...
报告 淮海战报
War communique from Huaihai
淮海总前委来电
According to the wire,
歼敌五十五万人 活捉杜聿明
550,000 enemies were killed and Du Yuming was captured.
新五军 十八军呢
What about the New 5th and the 18th?
全部吃掉
Gone.
五大主力全军覆灭
The 5 major divisions were wiped out.
老蒋 再无翻身之日了
Chiang is finished for good.
长江以北 从此再无大战了
There'll be no more fighting north of the Yangtze.
来 干
Cheers.
这是最后的斗争
This is the last battle.
团结起来到明天
We stay united till tomorrow.
英特纳雄耐尔
Internationale
就一定要实现
will come true.
这是最后的斗争
This is the last battle.
团结起来到明天
We stay united till tomorrow.
英特纳雄耐尔 就一定要实现
"Internationale" will come true.
父亲 这地上多凉啊
Father, it's cold on the ground.
你也坐吧
Sit down.
经儿
Ching-kuo.
你在上海做得很好 我很欣慰
You did a good job in Shanghai. I'm very pleased.
陈诚赴任台湾省主席
I made Chen Cheng Governor of Taiwan.
你明白为什么吗
Do you know why?
父亲已经在部署后路了
Your route of retreat?
是啊 杜聿明全军覆没
Yes, Du Yuming's men were wiped out.
能打仗的老兵损失殆尽
I lost all the men who can fight.
靠江南抓来的一百多万壮丁
We can't count on the 1 million men we captured in Jiangnan
他们是连枪都端不稳的
They can barely hold their rifles
长江 守不住了
The Yangtze is lost.
父亲 我们真的要退守台湾吗
You intend to evacuate to Taiwan?
你也去
You're coming too.
您认为 李宗仁的和谈建议
You think Li Zongren won't get anywhere
不会得到中共的响应吗
with the CPC over the peace negotiations?
战场上打不赢
If we can't defeat them at war,
谈判桌上怎么谈结果都是一样的
we won't beat them at the conference table
李宗仁白崇禧
Li Zongren and Bai Chongxi thought
自以为能和中共划江而治
the CPC will settle for using the Yangtze as a partition
他们太不了解毛泽东
They don't know Mao Zedong.
那毛泽东就一定不会接受
Mao will never agree to
南北分治的局面吗
separate governments on both sides of the Yangtze?
换做是你 你会接受吗
Would you accept if it were you?
这要看美国和苏联的态度 还有
That'd depend on the US and the USSR...
没那么复杂 谁的态度也不用看
Don't make it so complicated. It doesn't matter what anyone thinks
南北朝可以出现在过去
China was split into north and south in the past
但绝不会出现在今天
but not today.
谁敢当这个千古的罪人
Who would want to be blamed for it?
这胆量我没有
Definitely not me
张澜先生
Mr. Zhang Lan
您认为此时此刻
Right now, in your opinion,
中共会接受政府的求和声明吗
will the CPC accept the Government's plea for peace?
绝无可能
Impossible.
为什么会是这样
Why is that?
蒋介石不放弃所谓宪法
If Chiang never gives up his so-called constitution,
不要说共产党不会认
The CPC will not recognize it
人民也不会认
and neither will the people.
您对毛泽东周恩来很了解
You know Mao Zedong and Zhou Enlai very well.
他们这些人究竟是本土的革命家
Are they local revolutionaries
还是共产国际情报局在中国的代理人呢
or mere agents working for international communist intelligence bureau?
这个时候 这还算是个问题吗
What kind of question is that?
是问题 我想知道您的态度
I want to know your view.
我的态度是 中共顺应了民意
My view is that the CPC catered for the people
所以才有今天的成就
which explains their achievements today.
成就
Achievements?
对 成就
Yes, achievements.
宜生兄大鉴
Dear Zuoyi
相处多年 彼此深知
You and I have come a long way.
兄今厄于形势 自作主张
Given the circumstances, you took matters into your own hands.
无可奈何 弟惟求一事
There's nothing I can do about that, but I have one request.
明日起 派飞机抵平
I will send planes to Beiping tomorrow
运走十三军少校以上军宫
to airlift officers of the 13th Army ranked Major or above
及必要武器
and essential weaponry
望念多年契好 予以协肋
On account of our long standing friendship, please help me out.
蒋中正
Chiang Chung-cheng.
北平沦陷 傅作义投降
Beiping fell Fu Zuoyi surrendered.
共军又逼近长江 逼近南京
The CPC is moving in on the Yangtze and Nanjing.
我发出求和声明
With regards to my plea for peace,
中共虽然接受了
the CPC accepted it
却提出八项极端苛刻之条件
but raised 8 very harsh conditions.
夫人 只有您出面代表政府
Madame, if you speak on behalf of the Government,
毛周二人才可能相信我李宗仁
Mao and Zhou may trust me.
代总统 你是知道的
As you know, Mr. Acting President,
自内战重开之时 我就不问政事了
I washed my hands in politics since the onset of the civil war.
前几天报纸传谣说要我出山
There are rumors in the newspapers about me coming out of retirement.
基金会还正式出面辟谣
The Trust had to issue a denial.
夫人
Madame.
国民党乃中山先生所创建
Dr. Sun founded the KMT.
您总不能眼睁睁的看着它
You can't sit back and
万劫不复
watch it go to ruin.
别忘了 你虽然当了代总统
Don't forget, you may be the Acting President,
但蒋介石还是国民党的总裁
but Chiang Kai-shek is still the Party Chairman.
看来 李代总统的日子不好过呀
Looks like the Acting President is having a hard time.
是啊 蒋介石名义上退位
Chiang stepped down in name only
可依旧操纵着背后的一切
He still has control of everything.
李宗仁手上没有足够的权力
Li Zongren does not have enough authority.
实际上是个傀儡
He's only a puppet
这样的谈判是不会有结果的
Nothing will come out of the negotiation.
怪不得您不肯答应李代总统
No wonder you turned him down
我只是不愿意去北平
I don't want to go to Beiping
中山先生病逝在那里 伤心之地啊
because Dr. Sun died there. Too many memories.
表老 您是同盟会的前辈
Master Zhang, you're a veteran of the United League
朱德的老师
and Zhu De's mentor
周恩来和董必武都很佩服您的
Zhou Enlai and Dong Biwu have great respect for you.
代总统发表了和谈声明
The Acting President issued a declaration for peace negotiation
这居中调停之重任就非您老莫属了
You're the most suitable person to mediate.
中共既然提出了八项条件
If the CPC brought up 8 conditions,
你们谈就是了
go ahead and talk to them.
毛泽东若真肯谈的话
If Mao wants to talk,
怎么会提出这么苛刻的条件
he wouldn't raise these harsh conditions.
谈判谈判 总要有得谈才是
There should be room to negotiate in a negotiation.
所以李代总统让我去跟中共讨价还价
That's why the Acting President sent me to haggle with them
是居中调停
To mediate.
你们知道 政府已经取缔了民盟
As you know, the Government clamped down on the CDL.
如今民盟是个非法组织
It is now an illegal organization
我与中共是一党喽
I'm now in the same party as the Communists.
表老 您不要生气
Please don't be upset, sir.
那是蒋先生的命令
Mr Chiang issued that order,
跟代总统不相干的
not the Acting President.
我张澜站在革命一边
I side with the revolutionary.
还能替敌人讨价还价吗
I won't haggle for the enemy
表老
Sir.
送客
See them out
隔江而治 中国不是朝鲜
A partitioned rule? China is not Korea.
长江也不是三八线
The Yangtze is not the 38th Parallel.
给渡江前委发电报
Wire the General Front Committee.
他们渡江作战的计划批准了
Their war plan has been approved
中央的意见定在四月下旬
The central government advises to move the plan up to end of April
嗨 走
Go
快点 快点 好了没有
Hurry Are you ok?
别挤 别挤 别挤别挤
Don't push
林彪啊 还这么瘦啊
Lin Biao is still so skinny.
一百多万国民党军装进肚子里
Eating 1 million Nationalist soldiers
还没把他吃胖了
didn't even make him fat
同志们
Comrades
我代表中央政治局书记处宣布
On behalf of the Secretariat of the Central Politburo, I hereby announce
中国共产党第七届中央委员会
the commencement of the second meeting
第二次会议 开幕
of the 7th CPC Central Committee.
校长 张澜那边怎么办
What should we do about Zhang Lan?
他说打死都不去台湾
He'd rather die than go to Taiwan.
留着肯定是祸害
He's trouble to us if he stays.
那就成全他
Give him what he wants
报告
Sir.
去 把张澜干掉
Get rid of Zhang Lan.
局座 张澜可是有影响的人呐
He's a man of influence, sir
越是这样 越要干掉
The more reason to get rid of him.
懂了
I see
是公开的还是秘密的
Openly or privately?
这种事怎么能公开呢
How can you do this openly?
还是那句老话 活不见人
Like I said, don't let me see him alive.
死不见尸
And no body if he's dead.
杀的一定要干净
Don't make a mess.
是 懂了
I understand
去吧
Go on.
保重
Take care
站住
Stop
你们出去
Get out.
你就是张澜
Are you Zhang Lan?
你是什么人
Who are you?
你们要干什么
What do you want?
我是国民党稽查大队副大队长阎锦文
Deputy Chief Yan Jinwen of the Shanghai Inspectorate
受中共地下党的委托 协助你们出去
On behalf of the CPC, I will get you out
请你们务必相信我
Trust me.
阎大哥
Brother Yan.
早啊 当班啊
Morning, you're on duty?
最近不是查得严嘛
Security has been tightened lately
这是去哪里啊
Where are you going?
我们局里的公务
On Inspectorate business.
公私兼顾 老爷子也在车上
Mixing pleasure with business. My father is in the car.
阿华 别为难你 该查就查
Go ahead, do what you have to
不用 走吧
No need, run along
走了啊
Bye.
兄弟们 放行
Let them through
你要把我们带哪去
Where are you taking us?
北边
Up north
恩来 主席呢
Enlai, where's the Chairman?
买烟去了
Went to get smokes.
转了两条街 没看见一个商店开门营业
Not a shop is open in two blocks.
成俊同志 你是县委书记
Chengjun, you're the county committee secretary.
这可不行
This can't go on.
进城后 传言说
After entering the city, rumor has it
资本家和商人全是剥削阶级
capitalists and businessmen are exploiters
要革他们的命
and we should punish them.
吓得这些商人买卖全不敢做了
They're so scared no one is open for business.
这不是个小问题
This is not a small matter.
闹革命 我们天下第一
Revolution is our forte
搞经济 我们可比不了他们
but not economics.
没了商贩 连香烟都买不到
Can't even get smokes without the merchants,
还谈什么市场繁荣
let alone market prosperity.
要把人家请回来
We need the capitalists back.
观阶段还不能消灭资本家
At this stage, we can't eliminate them yet.
生产关系的改变不是过家家
Production must be handled with care.
不能胡来 一旦搞出了问题
If anything goes wrong,
那比在战场上打了败仗还糟糕
it'll be worse than losing a battle.
要有自知之明
We must know our limits
这些事我们需要从头学起
We must learn from scratch.
政治协商 协商的对象就是
The gist of political consultation
资产阶级政党和民主人士
involves capitalists and democracy activists.
我们是请人家来共同执政的
We invite them to help run the country,
不是来消灭人家的
not to eliminate them.
这个问题必须明确 搞垮了人家
We must be very clear on this: If we destroy them
自己又不懂得经营生产
and we can't run production on our own,
工厂倒闭 工人失业
factories will close down and worker will lose their jobs.
这不是砸自己饭碗么
We'll be smashing our own rice bowls.
这个饭碗我们刚刚端上 砸不得
We barely got our hands on them, don't smash them.
同志们 今天有两个要求
Comrades, we ask two things of you.
挺直腰板 声音洪亮 明白吗
Keep your backs straight and your voices up, understand?
听明白啦
Yes.
毛主席
Chairman Mao
傅将军 不敢当啊
General Fu, you flatter me.
我曾经说过 兵败之日要为您牵马
I promised to hold your horsewhip if I lose.
今天我给您开门
Today, I'll hold the door for you.
你没有败 败的人在南京
You did not lose The loser is in Nanjing.
不要为我开门 要请大家帮助我们
Don't hold the door for me
打开新中国的大门
Help me open the door for a new China.
敬礼
Salute
报告
Sir.
我是红二十八团的老兵
I'm with the 28th Army
今天带领塔山团
I'm here with the Tashan troops
奉命参加阅兵式
to join the dress parade.
我代表
On behalf of
活着的 死了的 红军老战士
soldiers of the Red Army, dead or alive,
向毛委员 敬礼
I salute you, Chairman Mao.
向前 向前 向前
Forward...
毛主席 万岁 万岁 万岁 万岁
Long live Chairman Mao
这就是润公三年前在重庆
Are these the 100,000 used guns
所说的那几十万条破枪吗 中共建党
you mentioned in Chongqing three years ago?
说长不长 说短不短了
The CPC has come a long way
毛主席万岁 万岁 万岁 万岁
Long live Chairman Mao
朱总司令万岁 万岁 万岁 万岁
Long live Commander Zhu
毛主席万岁 万岁 万岁 万岁
Long live Chairman Mao
朱总司令万岁 万岁 万岁 万岁
Long live Commander Zhu
毛主席万岁 万岁 万岁 万岁
Long live Chairman Mao
谈也是过江 不谈也是过江
Since they're crossing the Yangtze River anyway,
那还谈个屁
what the hell is the point of negotiation?
不打就缴枪 我是军人 我不干
To surrender before the fight begins? I'm a soldier, I won't do it.
中共表示 你和老蒋不一样
The CPC knew you're different from Chiang.
毛泽东知道你喜欢兵
Mao knows you enjoy being in the army.
他亲口跟我说 今后还让你继续带兵
He personally told me you might continue to command the troops
三十万 四十万 都行
up to as many as 400,000
笑话 我本来就是民国的国防部长
Nonsense. I'm already the Minister of National Defense.
德公 我们跟老蒋不和
Zongren, we don't get along with Chiang.
这是我们自己内部的事情
That's our internal business.
还轮不着共产党在我们脖子上拉屎拉尿
It's not up to the Communists to jack us around.
现在说这些 还有什么用
What's the use of saying that now?
那你说怎么办
What are you suggesting then?
等溪口的消息吧
Let's wait for word from Xikou.
英勇的人民解放军
300,000 courageous PLA
二十一日已有大约三十万人渡过长江
crossed the Yangtze River on the 21 st.
渡江战斗于二十日午夜开始
The campaign started at midnight on the 20th.
居然连一天都没能守住
Didn't even hold the defense line for one day.
何应钦政府正在撤退
He Yingqin is retreating.
据说是撤往广州
They say to Guangzhou.
我们和他们一起走吗
Shall we go with them?
为了合众国的利益
I have to look after the interests of the United States
我应该留在南京
I should stay here in Nanjing.
可我听说苏联大使馆
I heard the Soviet embassy
已经随政府向广州迁移了
had relocated to Guangzhou with the Government.
夫人早 早
Morning, Madam. Morning
枪炮声响了一夜 现在总算停了
The sound of gunfire went on all night. It finally stopped.
夫人 您好像没有休息好
Madam, you didn't sleep well.
我出去走走
I'll go for a walk.
您决定离开了
Have you decided to leave?
真的吗
Really?
毛主席好 你好啊
Hello, Chairman Mao.
毛主席好
您好 任公
Hello Jishen.
周先生好 你好 里边请
Mr. Zhou. This way, please.
主席 表老到了
Chairman, Zhang Lan is here.
润公 不敢当 不敢当
Mr. Mao, you flatter me
应该的 应该的
Not at all.
表老 你好啊 周公
Master Zhang, how are you? Mr Zhou
欢迎 里边请
Welcome, please come this way.
你好 表老
Hello, Master Zhang.
召开政协会议 成立中央人民政府
Calling the CPPCC to establish a new people's Government,
我们提议二位担任政府的副主席
I recommend you both for Vice Presidents.
我想当面听听二位的意见
I'd like to hear your opinion.
张澜听从安排
I'll go along with your arrangement.
任公有话要说
You have something to say?
这个提议 是你的意见
Is this your idea?
是中共中央的意见
The Central Committee's idea
我杀过你们共产党
I killed members of your party.
此一时彼一时啊
That was then, this is now.
如今我们是殊途同归
All roads lead to Rome.
可历史是无法改写的
We can't change history.
金无足赤 人无完人
Nobody's perfect.
个人的事再大也是小事
A personal matter, no matter how important, is a minor issue.
国家的事再小也是大事 为了新中国
A state matter, no matter how trivial, is a major issue, For the new state,
任公代表民革出任政府的副主席
be our Vice President on behalf of the Revolutionary Committee.
这是国家的事情
This is a state matter
过去的事不再提了
Forget the past.
今后中共愿与二位一起领导这个国家
The CPC is willing to work with you to lead this country.
肝胆相照 同舟共济
Let's help each other, as we're in the same boat now
携手创造新的历史
Together, we'll make history.
任潮服从安排
As you wish.
愿为华夏苍生尽绵薄之力
I'll do my best for China.
我们郑重建议中国同志
We strongly urge our comrades in China
应该尽快建立自己的政府
to set up their own government soon
苏联将会第一个
The USSR will, at the earliest time possible,
与新的中国建立外交关系
set up diplomatic relations with the new regime.
太好了
That's wonderful.
国民党疯狂轰炸上海 制造混乱
The frantic bombing of Shanghai by the KMT is causing chaos.
孙夫人的安全是个问题
I'm worried about Madam Sun's safety.
她是我党在危难中最忠诚的朋友
She's our most faithful friend when we were in dire straits
新政协召开在即
The new CPPCC is about to commence.
没有她的到来 天缺一角
It won't be complete without her.
我们这几个大男人
Men like us
说来说去也没个头绪
won't know how to talk to her.
还是派一名女同志去迎接孙夫人吧
Send a female comrade to escort her here.
恩来 还是请颖超辛苦一趟吧
Enlai, we'II burden Yingchao with the task
好主意
Good idea.
请周夫人去请孙夫人
Madam Zhou to escort Madam Sun.
好 事不宜迟 我去通知她
I'll tell her right away.
组建民主联合政府
To form a coalition government without you
没有您的参与
is something the Party will never agree to.
不只是我党 举国上下也不会答应
Neither would the rest of the country
我来 只是打个前站
I'm only the vanguard
我说不服您 恩来就会来
If I failed to convince you, Enlai would be next
他也说不服您 毛主席亲自来
and then Chairman Mao himself.
毛主席说 如果我们大家都说不服您
If we all failed to convince you,
就在政协会议上提个议案
we'd put this on the agenda of the CPPCC,
做个决议 派个代表团来
vote on it and send a delegation.
你们共产党人
You Communists
真是不达目的誓不罢休
won't stop until you get what you want.
夫人觉得这栋房子怎么样
What do you think of this house?
很不错 宽敞 明亮
Not bad, spacious and bright.
陈毅市长说了 这座房子就转交给先生了
Mayor Chen Yi said he'd giving it to you
您的中国福利基金会少年宫
as a permanent site for the youth center
就永久设在这里
of your China Welfare Fund.
孩子们可以天天到这儿来玩
The children can play in here every day.
那太好了
That's wonderful.
庆龄先生
Madam Sun
润之 今非昔比 这可使不得
Times have changed, Zedong. You mustn't do that.
旁人使不得 孙夫人使得
Only for Madam Sun.
谢谢你的邀请 谢谢邓颖超的陪同
Thanks for the invitation and Yingchao's company.
如今我党能够跟社会各界贤达
Now the Party can work with all delegates
在此共商建国大业
to build a new state,
要感谢夫人的支持和帮肋
I must thank your help and support.
夫人是国家和民族的功臣
You have been a great help to the country and its people
也是我党的恩人
and a benefactor of our Party.
各位代表
Fellow delegates,
一号图案中间的黄杠代表黄河
the yellow flag pole in the center of figure No 1 represents the Yellow River.
立意鲜明 赞成的请举手
It stands out. Those in favor, please raise your hands.
好 看来意见相对集中
Good. It's unilateral.
我反对
I object.
从美学观点
From an artistic perspective,
复字三十二号高出一筹
No. 32 is much better.
田汉先生是艺术家
Mr. Tian is an artist
对五颗星情有独钟啊
who's partial to the 5 stars.
这个方案的投稿者
The person who submitted this design
是上海的一个普通职员
is an ordinary clerk from Shanghai
第一轮被淘汰了 我又把它提了上来
It was disqualified in the first round, but I want to bring it up again.
是因为这个设计
Because this design
充满感情
is full of emotions.
我反对四颗星代表四个阶级的说法
I object to the version of the 4 stars representing the 4 classes.
还是一号旗黄河的图案比较好
I prefer the Yellow River pattern.
醒目 简洁
Simple and sharp.
赞成五星旗的有多少
How many in favor of the 5-star flag?
各位代表 徐悲鸿代表建议
Delegate Xu Beihong suggests
用《义勇军进行曲》作为国歌
we use "March of the Volunteers" as the national anthem
请大家发表意见
Let's hear your comments
曲子好 但歌词的内容应该改一改了
The melody is good, but we need to change the lyrics.
是啊 新中国即将成立
This is a new China.
原歌词的内容已不大符合国情
The original lyrics are outdated.
田汉先生 你是歌词作者
Mr. Tian Han, you're the lyricist.
你的意见呢
What's your opinion?
我不好表态 听大家的吧
I should refrain from commenting. I'll listen to the others.
我赞成 我赞成修改歌词
I agree we should change the lyrics
我们不能天天唱
We can't sing it every day,
特别是这句
especially this line:
中华民族到了最危险的时候
its greatest peril."
这不可行
It won't work
我反对 法国的《马赛曲》
I disagree, "La Marseillaise" of France
就是一首很悲壮的歌曲 一直传唱至今
is tragic but has been handed down till now
法国是法国 中国是中国
That's France, not China
诸位 这首歌词提醒我们
The lyrics of the song remind us
千万不要忘记过去 我赞同
not to forget the past. I agree
新中国要新国歌 展现新面貌
New China needs a new song for its new outlook.
为什么非要用一首老电影的插曲呢
Why use a song from an old movie?
请李济深代表讲话
What about you, Mr. Li?
《义勇军进行曲》为抗战而生
was written for the war
我唱过 唱得热血沸腾
I sang it before. It's inspirational and gets my blood boiling.
用血肉筑成我们新的长城
become our new Great Wall".
要记住历史
We must remember history.
这个歌词无需修改
No need to change the lyrics.
任公说的好
Well said.
我也是一个有危机感的人 赞成
Agree. I have a good sense for danger too
主席的意思 是保留原有歌词
The Chairman wishes to keep the original lyrics.
那位代表的意见呢 我看你老是举手
What about you? You kept raising your hand.
他们都替我讲了 没意见
They took the words out of my mouth I have no comment.
那我就多说一句
Let me say just one thing.
居安思危也是一个民族成熟的表现
To be vigilant in peace time is what a mature nation should do
至于改不改由田汉先生自己定吧
We'll let Mr. Tian Han decide
那 不改吧
Then let's keep the lyrics.
毛主席 各位代表
Chairman Mao, fellow delegates.
咱们照了啊
Are you ready?
各位代表看这 咱们要照了啊
Look over here, ready.
这位男同志 我们是妇女代表
This is a women's delegation.
主席 大家都在议论国旗的图案
Chairman, everyone is talking about the pattern on the national flag.
你的意见呢
What do you think?
我同意加上黄河那幅
I like the Yellow River.
我反对
I disagree.
师傅 您能修底版吗 能啊
Can you fix the negative? Yes.
把我旁边人修掉
Take out the person next to me.
你旁边十多个人呢
There are over 10 people next to you.
不是 就那挤进来男同志
I mean the man who jammed in
哦 成 谢谢你啊
Alright. Thank you
听人劝吃饱饭 说说你的道理
What's your reason?
主席 我也认为在国旗中间加一条横杠
Chairman, adding a pole to the middle
有点儿把国家分开的感党
gives the impression of splitting up the country.
我不知道这样想是不是正确
Is that the right interpretation?
没这么严重吧 很多人都主张这一幅啊
Can't be that serious. Most people prefer this one
龚澎 你的意见呢
Gong Peng, what do you think?
我们都喜欢复字三十二号
We like No 32
把五颗星安排在旗帜的左角上
Placing five stars in the left corner
四颗小星环绕
with four small stars surrounding
每颗小星都有一角冲着大星 很好看
and their tips pointing at the big star It looks pretty.
主席 大星居中 代表中国共产党
Chairman, the big star in the middle represents the Party
四颗小星代表告个阶级
while the small ones represent the 4 classes
寓意也准确
The symbolism is correct.
毛主席 看到这面旗帜 能让人充满热情
Looking at this flag makes one feel enthusiastic.
热情
Enthusiastic?
反正看到这面旗 我们就特别的激动
I feel excited when I look at the flag.
主席 孙夫人也喜欢这个设计
Madam Sun likes this design too.
夫人遗访欧美 意见有代表性
You have been abroad, your opinion should count
请夫人谈谈吧
Please tell us what you think.
五星红旗的图案反映了中国的实际状况
The five stars design is a good representation of China's situation.
在中国共产党的领导下
Under the leadership of the CPC,
各个阶级团结向心 一起建设新中国
all the classes are united to build a new China
旗帜本身鲜艳 庄重 大气
The color is sharp, solemn and grand.
中国的实际 大家的团结 说得好
The truth is, China is united. Well said.
现在要团结 将来要团结 永远要团结
We're united now and we'll always be in the future.
轰炸北平的计划到底可不可行
Is the air raid on Beiping feasible?
总裁想听一下你们空军的意见
The Chairman wants feedback from the Air Force.
飞行的半径过大
The flying radius is too big.
飞机必须中途降落加油
The planes must re-tank somewhere
否则将有去无回
or they won't make it back.
外交部已经在联系驻韩美军
The Ministry of Foreign Affairs has liaised with the Americans in Korea
这方面你可以放心
You can rest assured.
共军已经拥有空军了
But the CPC has its air force now.
总裁只想听你一句话
The Chairman only wants to know
执行轰炸任务 能还是不能 就那么简单
if the air raid is feasible. That's all.
困难再多 只要总裁下令
Despite the difficulties, as long as he issues the order,
一定完成任务
we'll get it done.
诸位代表先生们
Fellow delegates,
全国人民所渴望的政协会议
the CPPCC that the whole country is looking forward to
现在开幕了
will now commence.
现在的中国人民政治协商会议
The new CPPCC
是在完全新的基础之上召开的
will commence on a brand new foundation
它具有代表全国人民的性质
It represents the Chinese people
它获得全国人民的信任和拥护
and has the people's faith and support
因此 中国人民政治协商会议宣布
Therefore, the CPPCC hereby announces
自己执行全国人民代表大会的职权
its right to call this meeting
诸位代表先生们
Fellow delegates,
我们有一个共同的感觉
we have a consensus
这就是我们的工作
that our work here
将写在人类的历史上
will go down in history.
它表明 占人口四分之一的中国人
It proves that China, which accounts for 1/4 of the world's population,
从此 站立起来了
is finally on her feet
中国的命运已经操在人民自己手里
The destiny of China is in the hands of her people
中国就将如太阳升起在东方那样
China will rise like the sun in the east.
以自己辉煌的光焰普照大地
Its radiance will illuminate the land
迅速荡涤反动政府留下的污泥浊水
and cleanse the filth and mire left behind by the reactionary government.
治好战争创伤 建立起一个
Heal the wounds of war and build a brand new
崭新的 强盛的 名副其实的人民共和国
and powerful People's Republic of China.
中华人民共和国万岁
Long live the People's Republic of China.
民主联合政府万岁
Long live the Coalition Government.
全国人民大团结万岁
Long live the unity of the people
总裁 空军周总司令报告
According to Commander Zhou,
飞机已进入一级状态
the planes are in Class A status.
随时可以起飞轰炸北平
They're ready to bombard Beiping any time.
可是 美国拒绝飞机降落釜山加油
But the US has turned down our request to refuel in Pusan.
什么意思
What does that mean?
一旦起飞 所有战机将无法返航
They can't come back after takeoff.
毛泽东的开国大典 几点举行
What time is Mao's founding ceremony?
下午三点 天安门
3pm at Tiananmen Square.
天数啊 国民党败在自己的手里喽
It's fate. The KMT is ruined with our own hands
任务取消吧
Cancel the mission
是
Yes, sir
中华人民共和国
The People's Republic of China and
中央人民政府
the Central People's Government
今天 成立了
have been established today
---==--- 谢谢观赏 ---==---
--=阿武家园:www.bt521.net=--